<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-21425</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076123</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Collective Response of Zebrafish Shoals to a Free-Swimming Robotic Fish</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Response of Zebrafish Shoals to a Robotic Fish</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butail</surname><given-names>Sachit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartolini</surname><given-names>Tiziana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porfiri</surname><given-names>Maurizio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, Polytechnic Institute of New York University, Brooklyn, New York, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Planas</surname><given-names>Josep V.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Universitat de Barcelona, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">mporfiri@poly.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MP SB. Performed the experiments: TB SB. Analyzed the data: SB MP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SB MP. Wrote the paper: SB MP TB.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<elocation-id>e76123</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Butail et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In this work, we explore the feasibility of regulating the collective behavior of zebrafish with a free-swimming robotic fish. The visual cues elicited by the robot are inspired by salient features of attraction in zebrafish and include enhanced coloration, aspect ratio of a fertile female, and carangiform/subcarangiform locomotion. The robot is autonomously controlled with an online multi-target tracking system and swims in circular trajectories in the presence of groups of zebrafish. We investigate the collective response of zebrafish to changes in robot speed, achieved by varying its tail-beat frequency. Our results show that the speed of the robot is a determinant of group cohesion, quantified through zebrafish nearest-neighbor distance, which increases with the speed of the robot until it reaches <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We also find that the presence of the robot causes a significant decrease in the group speed, which is not accompanied by an increase in the freezing response of the subjects. Findings of this study are expected to inform the design of experimental protocols that leverage the use of robots to study the zebrafish animal model.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by the National Science Foundation under Grant nos. CMMI-0745753 and CMMI-1129820 and the Mitsui USA Foundation through a fellowship to Tiziana Bartolini. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The use of engineered stimuli to study animal behavior is both inspired by and aids in the understanding of animal perception. In this context, animated images <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Death1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Gerlai1">[2]</xref>, virtual projections <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Ioannou1">[3]</xref>, and robots <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Krause1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Webb1">[5]</xref> have been recently integrated into the design of experimental protocols to conduct hypothesis-driven studies of animal behavior. Among these, robots are expected to provide the largest degree of control through the exploitation of other sensory modalities beyond vision <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Partan1">[6]</xref> and through their three-dimensional presence and mobility in the environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Halloy1">[7]</xref>. These features allow for the synthesis of a dynamic, yet controllable, stimulus that can elicit a meaningful response in the experimental subjects<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Krause1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Ward1">[8]</xref>.</p>
<p>This interdisciplinary research area at the interface of ethology and robotics is often referred to as ''ethorobotics'' <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Partan1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Todd1">[9]</xref>. Existing robot designs for ethorobotics research can be broadly classified in two categories based on their mobility. Those that mimic animal body movements while being anchored to a single location <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Partan1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Patricelli1">[10]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-FernandezJuricic1">[19]</xref> and those that cover spatial ground without any appreciable body movement <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Halloy1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Ward1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Vaughan1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Rossi1">[23]</xref>. Anchored robots that mimic body movements have been used to study multi-sensory alarm signals in squirrels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Partan1">[6]</xref>, male courtship response to female behavior in satin bowerbirds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Patricelli1">[10]</xref>, social information transfer in three different bird species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-FernandezJuricic1">[19]</xref>, and fish response to biomimetic locomotion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Marras1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Kopman1">[14]</xref>. Spatial control of robots has been particularly effective in the study of group response. For example, mobile robots releasing pheromones in the environment were used to explore shelter seeking in cockroaches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Halloy1">[7]</xref>, robotic replicas moving on a guide line were used to study quorum decision making in sticklebacks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Ward1">[8]</xref>, and a robotic sheepdog was used to control a flock of ducks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Vaughan1">[20]</xref>. In freshwater fish species that use vision as a primary sensory modality, both these form of movements have been used individually to modulate animal behavior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Abaid1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Polverino2">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Polverino3">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Swain1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Faria1">[24]</xref>.</p>
<p>In this work, we integrate these two forms of movements in a robotic fish that propels itself through a carangiform/subcarangiform body undulation to freely swim in a test tank. The free-swimming capability allows the robot to actively interact with live subjects in different areas of the experimental tank, while the body undulations are expected to enhance its degree of biomimicry. Moreover, body undulations can elicit salient flow cues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Marras1">[11]</xref>, which have been shown to be determining factors in the spatial arrangements of fish schools <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Herskin1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Svendsen1">[26]</xref>. We utilize such robotic fish to investigate the collective response of groups of zebrafish.</p>
<p>Zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) are rapidly emerging as an experimental species for the investigation of functional and dysfunctional biological processes, due to the sequencing of their genome, their high reproduction rate, short intergeneration time, prominent shoaling tendency, and elevated stocking density compared to laboratory mammals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Grunwald1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Miller2">[32]</xref>. For example, zebrafish are extensively used to study the effects of drugs of abuse and ethanol administration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Gerlai2">[33]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Grossman1">[36]</xref>. Furthermore, with the aim of generating high-throughput behavioral data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Gerlai3">[37]</xref>, considerable research is being performed to integrate animated images of conspecifics, heterospecifics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Saverino1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Abaid2">[39]</xref>, and predators <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Gerlai1">[2]</xref> in experimental paradigms. In the context of ethorobotics, we have recently proposed a series of dichotomous preference tests to study zebrafish response to an anchored robotic fish whose design is inspired by salient features of attraction in zebrafish. Specifically, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Abaid1">[12]</xref>, it is shown that zebrafish responds differentially to variation in aspect ratio and color in the robotic fish; in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Polverino1">[13]</xref>, it is demonstrated that zebrafish shoals prefer such a robotic fish to an empty compartment; in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Kopman1">[14]</xref>, it is demonstrated that an interactive robot, whose tail-beat frequency responds to fish position, is able to induce preference among single organisms; and in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Polverino3">[17]</xref>, it is shown that the robotic fish is able to simultaneously attract shoals of zebrafish while repelling shoals of mosquitofish that would otherwise display aggressive behavior. Finally, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Spinello1">[16]</xref>, the robotic fish is utilized as a tool to analyze the effect of ethanol administration on zebrafish behavior.</p>
<p>The robotic fish has a body and a tail section and moves in water by beating its tail section at preset frequencies; it turns by offsetting the tail beat at an angle to the main body. A real-time visual tracking system uses an overhead camera view to remotely steer the robot into circular trajectories. We use this capability to test the hypothesis that the locomotion of the robotic fish differentially modulates zebrafish behavior. Specifically, we change the speed of the robotic fish by varying the tail-beat frequency of the robotic fish, while keeping the tail beat amplitude constant. To control for the effects of the tail beating and the visual cues from the robot, additional tests are performed in which the robot is beating its tail at a constant frequency in a fixed position in the tank or is completely absent. We expect the following predictions to be met: (i) a free-swimming robot whose design and movement are inspired by a zebrafish will not elicit fear response in zebrafish; (ii) the subjects will change their social interaction in the presence of the robotic fish; and (iii) the speed of the robotic fish will differentially modulate fish collective behavior.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Ethics statement</title>
<p>The experiments were conducted following the protocols AWOC-2012-101 and AWOC-2013-103 approved by the Animal Welfare Oversight Committee of the Polytechnic Institute of New York University.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Animals and housing</title>
<p>We used wild-type zebrafish in our experiments. The subjects, approximately <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in body length (6–8 months old), were acquired from an online aquarium source (LiveAquaria.com, Rhinelander, Wisconsin, USA). They were maintained in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) tanks with no more than 20 fish per tank under a 12 hours light/12 hours dark photoperiod <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Cahill1">[40]</xref>. The temperature and pH in the holding tanks were maintained at 27<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>1<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>C and 7.2, respectively. Fish were fed with commercial flake food (Hagen Corp./Nutrafin max, USA), at approximately 7 pm every day. Experiments were started after a ten day acclimatization period.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Robotic fish</title>
<p>Following the design in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Kopman2">[41]</xref>, the robotic fish was made of a rigid acrylonitrile butadiene styrene plastic and is divided into a body and tail section (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0076123-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) with a flexible caudal fin. The ratio between the length (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), height (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), and width (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) of the robot (aspect ratio) was designed to match that of a fertile zebrafish female. The body section contained a single cell lithium-ion polymer battery, an Arduino Pro mini microcontroller (Sparkfun electronics, USA), and a Nordic nRF2401A transceiver chip (Sparkfun electronics, USA). A Traxxas 2065 servomotor (Traxxas, Plano TX, USA) was inserted into the tail section and was used to actuate the body-tail joint, which, in turn, propelled the robot to move forward. The flexible caudal fin allowed for a sinuous undulation of the tail mimicking carangiform/subcarangiform patterns characteristic of zebrafish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Saverino1">[38]</xref>. The robot was positively buoyant in water so that it swam just under the surface of the water. The robot was painted bright blue with silver stripes and a yellow head to match zebrafish coloration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Rosenthal1">[42]</xref>. Color pattern, aspect ratio, and tail-beat frequency have been shown as relevant factors in the attractiveness of the robotic fish to live zebrafish<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Abaid1">[12]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0076123-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Robotic fish used in our experiments.</title>
<p>The color pattern, aspect ratio, and shape of the caudal fin of the mobile robotic fish used in our experiments matched that of a zebrafish.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The robot was controlled with a remote control unit consisting of an Arduino Duemilanove microcontroller (Sparkfun electronics, USA) and a Nordic nRF2401A transceiver chip (Sparkfun electronics, USA). The microcontroller unit was programmed to receive control parameters namely tail-beat frequency, tail-beat amplitude, and tail-section offset via a universal serial bus (USB). These parameters were then transmitted wirelessly to the robot every 3/5th of a second. In our experiments, we kept the tail-beat amplitude constant at 20 degrees. The heading of the robot was controlled by varying the tail-section offset from a trim value of zero degrees when the robot body was in line with the tail section.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Experimental setup</title>
<p>The subjects were filmed in a 120 <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> 120 <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> experimental tank supported on an aluminum frame. The water depth was maintained at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> during the experiments. The tank surface was covered with a white contact paper to obtain a high-contrast background for aid in tracking. A Microsoft LifeCam web camera was mounted <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> above the water surface to provide a single overhead video feed at a resolution of 640 <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> 480 pixels through a USB interface. Diffused overhead light from four 25 W fluorescent tubes (All-Glass Aquarium, preheat aquarium lamp, U.K.) was used to illuminate the observation region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0076123-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). A <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Pentium dual core desktop computer with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> memory ran the real-time multi-target tracking and control algorithm using the camera's input (see Supplementary text for details of tracking and control). The setup was isolated during the experiment with dark curtains. Experimental data consisting of image frames and trajectories, was backed up every night and a duplicate copy maintained for analysis.</p>
<fig id="pone-0076123-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Schematic of the experimental setup.</title>
<p>The experimental apparatus consisted of a square shallow tank with overhead ultraviolet lighting and camera for real-time tracking.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Experimental procedure</title>
<p>The experimental conditions consisted of the robot swimming in the experimental tank with three zebrafish (Fig. S1 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0076123.s001">File S1</xref>). Four conditions were tested to evaluate the hypothesis that the locomotion of a robotic fish differentially modulates the behavior of zebrafish groups. These conditions comprised a robot not beating its tail in a static position, and then beating its tail at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as it swam in circular trajectories of constant radius. For brevity, these conditions are referred to as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. These tail-beat frequencies correspond to robot speeds of approximately <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, respectively, and were selected to explore variations in the reference condition corresponding to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which was considered in the preference tests described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Abaid1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Kopman1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Spinello1">[16]</xref>. To compensate for the effect of noise, the servo motor was kept on during the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> condition although the tail of the robot was not moving.</p>
<p>To control for the effects of the tail-beat and for the visual cues associated with the presence of the robot in the tank, we conducted two additional experimental conditions. In one condition, called Fixed, the robot was held in a place within the tank at different positions with its tail beating at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and in the other condition, called No robot, the fish were observed without the robot in the tank. The radius of the circular trajectory, whenever the robot was swimming, was set at a constant value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (Fig. S2 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0076123.s001">File S1</xref>). A total of 144 subjects, distributed over 48 trials with three naive subjects in each trial, were used to conduct the experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0076123-g003">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0076123-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>A summary of the experimental conditions.</title>
<p>We considered tail-beat frequencies of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> corresponding to swimming speeds of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. To control for the tail-beating movement and the presence of the robot, we conducted tests with the robot anchored to preset locations in the tank and without the robot.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>In each trial, fish in groups of three were transferred into the experimental tank with a hand net. The tracking and control system was initiated immediately after. The tracking system automatically computed the background and intensity threshold. The intensity threshold was lowered from a high value in successive frames until three distinct targets were obtained consistently. The robot communication and trim settings were tested next by beating the tail about the center, followed by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> offset. After testing, the robot was positioned at a predetermined starting point located near the tank corner. A habituation time of ten minutes with the robot set stationary was given to avoid novelty effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Polverino1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Cianca1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Wong1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Bass1">[44]</xref>. During this time, the servomotor was turned on with the tail-beat amplitude set to zero to create a uniform acoustic background. The start signal was transmitted to the robot at the end of the habituation time followed by a five minute experimental session. For experiments in which the robot was stationary during the trial time (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and Fixed), the robot was anchored from the bottom to a transparent plexiglass sheet at equally spaced locations around the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> circular trajectory.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>The experiments were recorded at five frames per second for five minutes each, resulting in a total of 1500 frames per trial. Trajectory data was verified and repaired if needed for each individual trial using a custom MATLAB script.</p>
<p>The degree of cohesion of zebrafish groups was described in terms of the average nearest-neighbor distance (ANND) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Webster1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Kolpas1">[46]</xref>. Given the two-dimensional position <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-th fish at frame <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the ANND during that frame is <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Kolpas1">[46]</xref> <disp-formula id="pone.0076123.e047"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e047" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the total number of fish and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes the standard Euclidean norm. Group coordination was captured through the polarization (Pol) that measures the degree of alignment between the directions of motion of the fish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Vicsek1">[47]</xref>. Given the two-dimensional velocity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-th fish at frame <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the polarization at that frame is<disp-formula id="pone.0076123.e053"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e053" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the direction of motion. The group speed given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was computed to describe average speed of the subjects. Group interaction with the robotic fish was quantified in terms of three values, namely, the average distance to the robot, the minimum distance to the robot, and the relative group speed. Minimum distance to the robot was computed by comparing the individual fish distances to the robot center on the image, and relative group speed is defined as the difference between group speed and the speed of the robot.</p>
<p>To elucidate the behavior of the subjects, we scored the time spent freezing during each trial. This value was computed automatically from the trajectory data. In particular a fish was considered freezing during a frame if it spent two continuous seconds within a ball of radius of 2 cm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Kopman1">[14]</xref>. Freezing was recorded if at least one fish satisfied this condition.</p>
<p>To evaluate the effect of robot locomotion, a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with the ANND, Pol, average speed, average distance to the robot, minimum distance to the robot, and time spent freezing, each as a dependent variable, and the robot speed as the independent variable was used. Tukey HSD post-hoc tests were performed to compare these quantities between pairs of robot speeds if a significant effect was found. Statistical power for the given sample size of 32 (4 conditions <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>8 experimental groups each) was confirmed (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) using average nearest neighbor distance and speed as the measurement variables. In particular, corresponding values of shoaling and schooling from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Miller2">[32]</xref> were used to compute the effect size (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) with the expectation that over the full range of robot speeds the values of ANND and group speed will change one body length and 3 cm/s respectively. To evaluate the effect of time, a two-way ANOVA with the same dependent variables, but time of observation in minutes and robot speed as the independent variables (eight replicates for each minute of the five minute experimental session), was performed. One-way ANOVA was used to compare control conditions with select test conditions. Significance level for all tests was set at p<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Statistics were computed using MATLAB (R2011a, Mathworks) and power analysis was performed using G*Power 3.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Faul1">[48]</xref>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Group cohesion</title>
<p>A comparison of ANND values across test conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0076123-g004">Fig. 4</xref>) indicates a significant difference with change in robot speed (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The value of ANND initially rises with the robot speed and then drops as the robot speed is increased further. Post-hoc analysis shows that the maximum (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and minimum (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) values of ANND are attained at robot speeds of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> respectively. Individual comparisons show that the maximum value of ANND is significantly different from those attained when the robot is stationary and when the robot is swimming at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We do not observe a significant effect of the presence of the robot (No robot and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, p = 0.099) and effect of tail-beat movement only (Fixed and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, p = 0.243) on group cohesion.</p>
<fig id="pone-0076123-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Group cohesion changed significantly with robot speed.</title>
<p>Average nearest-neighbor distance between zebrafish as the robot moved at increasing speeds of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> corresponding to a tail-beat frequency of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> respectively. Control conditions (No robot and Fixed) are shown for reference. Error bars represent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> standard error mean.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Group coordination</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0076123-g005">Figure 5</xref> compares the polarization of the groups as a function of the robot speed. Therein, we observe an initial drop in the polarization as the robot speed increases from 0–<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> followed by an increase at the robot speed of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, however the effect of the robot speed on the polarization fails to reach statistical significance (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). We find that the presence of the robot (No robot and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, p = 0.172) and the effect of tail-beat movement only (Fixed and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, p = 0.740) do not change the coordination in zebrafish. Polarization distributions are bimodal (Fig. S7 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0076123.s001">File S1</xref>) with the fish being highly polarized for the majority of the time across conditions.</p>
<fig id="pone-0076123-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Group coordination was always high.</title>
<p>The polarization of zebrafish was not significantly different between conditions with the robot moving at varying speeds (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Control conditions (No robot and Fixed) are shown for reference. Error bars represent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> standard error mean.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Group speed</title>
<p>The group speed of the fish is not significantly affected by the robot speed (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). While the tail-beat movement of the robot does not produce a significant effect on group speed (Fixed and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, p = 0.375), the presence of the robot produces a significant change in the speed of the subjects (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and No robot, p = 0.0001). The highest value of group speed of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is observed in the absence of the robot (Fig. S3).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Fish-robot interactions</title>
<p>The average (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and the minimum distance of the zebrafish to the robot (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) appear to be related to the robot speed, however none of these dependencies reach statistical significance (Figs. S5 and S6 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0076123.s001">File S1</xref>). The average distance of the fish to the robot is more than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The largest difference of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> between the average and the minimum distance to the robot is observed in the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> condition. Relative group speed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0076123-g006">Fig. 6</xref>) changes significantly with the robot speed (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), with post-hoc analysis showing that the least difference of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (at robot speed at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) is significantly different from values when the robot is stationary and swimming at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0076123-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Group speed relative to the robot varied with robot speed.</title>
<p>The relative speed of zebrafish was significantly different between conditions with the robot moving at varying speeds (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Control conditions (No robot and Fixed) are shown for reference. Error bars represent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> standard error mean.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Group behavior</title>
<p>Between the test conditions, the speed of the robot does not alter the time spent freezing (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Similarly, neither the presence of the robot (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and No robot, p = 0.091), nor the effect of tail-beat movement only (Fixed and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, p = 0.689) significantly changes the time spent freezing by the zebrafish, although the mere presence appears to increase this time by a small percentage (Fig. S4 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0076123.s001">File S1</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3f">
<title>Time-effect</title>
<p>The effect of time is not significant in robot speed on cohesion (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), polarization (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and speed (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), distance to the robot (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), minimum distance to the robot (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), and time spent freezing (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) with no significant interaction between robot speed and time (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for all values).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The results of this study confirm that the robotic fish is not perceived as a conspecific by the zebrafish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Polverino1">[13]</xref>, whereby fish tend to maintain a considerably smaller distance between themselves than with the robot. At the same time, we discount the effects of novelty-induced fear to explain high cohesion in any of the conditions because of the ten minute habituation time. This value is almost twice the six minute habituation time that has been shown to significantly increase exploratory behavior and decrease instances of freezing in zebrafish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Wong1">[43]</xref>, even in the presence of a predator model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Cianca1">[18]</xref>. This inference is also supported on the basis of prior studies with the same robot, where a consistent spatial preference for the robot was found with similar habituation times <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Abaid1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Polverino1">[13]</xref>.</p>
<p>The results indicate that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, obtained with a tail-beat frequency of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, is a critical speed for the robotic fish, with increases above or below this threshold differentially affecting zebrafish collective response. In particular, we observe a significant decrease in the group cohesion and a continued decrease in the polarization of the zebrafish shoals as the robot increases its speed from 0 to 3<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The cohesion suddenly increases as the robotic fish speed is increased to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and is accompanied by a similar, though not significant, increase in polarization. Furthermore, at this tail beat frequency, we also find that fish vary their speed to match the robot speed, while exhibiting the maximum disparity between the average and the minimum distance from it. The latter evidence indicates that fish tend to leave the shoal to interact with the robotic fish when it beats the tail at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The variation in fish response as a function of robot speed is unlikely to be related to sensory cues generated by the body movement only, since the fish do not behave differently if the robot is fixed and beats its tail at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Therefore, we propose that visual cues associated with the motion of the robot at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.e124" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are relevant factors in shaping the interaction between the live subjects and the robotic fish.</p>
<p>It is possible that the robot is perceived as a predator in conditions where it is stationary or moving slowly. This argument is supported by findings in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Gerlai1">[2]</xref>, which indicate that zebrafish reduce their speed when confronted with a computer animated image of a predator. The hypothesis that the robot is perceived as a predator is also favored by the increase of fish cohesion as the robot is present in the tank. Indeed, an increase in cohesion is indicative of response to predatory threats <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Webster1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Tien1">[49]</xref>, alarm substances <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Speedie1">[50]</xref>, and novelty-induced fear <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Breder1">[51]</xref>. However, this change is not accompanied by an increased polarization, which is also associated with high threat perception in fish schools <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Miller2">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Bode1">[52]</xref>; in fact, polarization decreases with the introduction of the robot. The bimodal distributions of polarization show that the fish spend time either shoaling or schooling, suggesting that the decrease in polarization is due to an increased shoaling tendency of the fish. A second result that does not support the possibility that the robot is perceived as a predator is the absence of a time effect in the group interaction, quantified in terms of minimum and average distance to the robot. This is in contrast with experimental studies that demonstrate the increased avoidance of a predator with time in the form of increased distance from it <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Bass1">[44]</xref>. Although this independence over time can also be explained by a ceiling effect, zebrafish do not maximize their distance to the robot, ranging between 40–60 cm, in an environment that allows for maintaining distances as large as 90–100 cm. Finally, the freezing response of the subjects does not increase in the presence of the robot, as we would expect if the robot was perceived as a predator <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Bass1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Maximino1">[53]</xref>.</p>
<p>The presence of results both in favor and against the robot being perceived as a predator by the zebrafish posits the need for further studies on zebrafish perception of the robot motion. Although we did not measure the tail-beat frequency and amplitude of zebrafish in our experiments, the robot was designed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Abaid1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Kopman2">[41]</xref> to mimic the carangiform/subcarangiform swimming motion of zebrafish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Plaut1">[54]</xref>. In particular, the tail-section and passive caudal fin were approximately half the total body length of the robot. Despite offering a considerably less tail-beat frequency and speed than live zebrafish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Thomas1">[55]</xref>, the robot's locomotion is unlike a sympatric predator that would typically consist of short bursts of motion accompanied with long durations of stationary behavior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Bass1">[44]</xref>. Perhaps the visual cues associated with this slow, yet persistent, motion of the robot reduce the possibility of it being perceived as a predator.</p>
<p>This work shows that both body and spatial movements of the robotic fish differentially modulate zebrafish behavior. Specifically, by controlling for spatial movement and body movement separately we are able to highlight a combination where the fish tend to explore the unconstrained free-swimming environment. The ability to actively interact with fish in a large unconstrained environment is expected to improve our understanding of shoaling behavior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Buske1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Saverino1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Rosenthal1">[42]</xref>. The system described here is scalable with respect to both robots and animals and can track their behavior in real time.</p>
<p>Future work will be driven in several directions, including the dependence of zebrafish shoal size on its response <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0076123-Pritchard1">[56]</xref> to the robotic fish, and conversely, the dependence of the size and configuration of a shoal of robotic fish on zebrafish response.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0076123.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0076123.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>File S1</label><caption>
<p>Supporting information text detailing the multi-target tracking method, robot control design, and synopsis of experimental data on fish response.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to acknowledge assistance from Paul Phamduy, Vladislav Kopman, Fausto Del Sette, Pankaj Rajput, Fabrizio Ladu, and Violet Mwaffo in fabricating the robotic fish and independent verification of the trajectory data.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Death1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>D’eath</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Can video images imitate real stimuli in animal behaviour experiments?</article-title> <source>Biological Reviews</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Gerlai1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) responds to the animated image of a predator: towards the development of an automated aversive task</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>201</volume>: <fpage>318</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Ioannou1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannou</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guttal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couzin</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Predatory fish select for coordinated collective motion in virtual prey</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>337</volume>: <fpage>1212</fpage>–<lpage>1215</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Krause1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winfield</surname><given-names>AFT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deneubourg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Interactive robots in experimental biology</article-title>. <source>Trends in Ecology and Evolution</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Webb1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>What does robotics offer animal behaviour?</article-title> <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Partan1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Partan</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larco</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <collab xlink:type="simple">OwensMJ</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Wild tree squirrels respond with multisensory enhancement to conspecific robot alarm behaviour</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>1127</fpage>–<lpage>1135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Halloy1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halloy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sempo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caprari</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rivault</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asadpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Social integration of robots into groups of cockroaches to control self-organized choices</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>318</volume>: <fpage>1155</fpage>–<lpage>1158</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Ward1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>AJW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sumpter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couzin</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>PJB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Quorum decision-making facilitates information transfer in fish shoals</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>6948</fpage>–<lpage>6953</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Todd1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Mobile robots-the lessons from nature</article-title>. <source>Robots and Biological Systems: Towards a New Bionics</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Patricelli1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patricelli</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borgia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Male satin bowerbirds, <italic>Ptilonorhynchus violaceus</italic>, adjust their display intensity in response to female startling: an experiment with robotic females</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Marras1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marras</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porfiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Fish and robots swimming together: attraction towards the robot demands biomimetic locomotion</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Society Interface</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1856</fpage>–<lpage>1868</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Abaid1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abaid</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartolini</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porfiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Zebrafish responds differentially to a robotic fish of varying aspect ratio, tail beat frequency, noise, and color</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>233</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Polverino1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polverino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abaid</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kopman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macrì</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porfiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Zebrafish response to robotic fish: preference experiments on isolated individuals and small shoals</article-title>. <source>Bioinspiration &amp; Biomimetics</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>036019</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Kopman1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laut</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polverino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porfiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Closed-loop control of zebrafish response using a bioinspired robotic-fish in a preference test</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Society Interface</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>20120540</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Polverino2"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polverino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porfiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Mosquitofish (<italic>Gambusia affinis</italic>) responds differentially to a robotic fish of varying swimming depth and aspect ratio</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>250</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Spinello1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spinello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porfiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Acute ethanol administration affects zebrafish preference for a biologically-inspired robot</article-title>. <source>Alcohol</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Polverino3"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Polverino G, Porfiri M (2013) Zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) behavioural response to bioinspired robotic fish and mosquitofish (<italic>Gambusia affinis</italic>) (to appear). Bioinspiration &amp; Biomimetics.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Cianca1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cianca V, Bartolini T, Porfiri M, Macri S (2013) A robotics-based behavioral paradigm to measure anxiety-related responses in zebrafish (to appear). PLoS ONE.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-FernandezJuricic1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Juricic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kowalski</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Where does a flock end from an information perspective? A comparative experiment with live and robotic birds</article-title>. <source>Behavioral Ecology</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1304</fpage>–<lpage>1311</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Vaughan1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sumpter</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Experiments in automatic flock control</article-title>. <source>Robotics and Autonomous Systems</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-deMargerie1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Margerie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lumineau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Influence of a mobile robot on the spatial behaviour of quail chicks</article-title>. <source>Bioinspiration &amp; Biomimetics</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Swain1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couzin</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Real-time feedback-controlled robotic rish for behavioral experiments with fish schools</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the IEEE</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Rossi1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rossi C, Coral W, Barrientos A (2012) Robotic Fish to Lead the School. In: Palstra AP, Planas JV, editors, Swimming Physiology of Fish, Springer Berlin Heidelberg. pp. 407–421.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Faria1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>JRG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clément</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couzin</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A novel method for investigating the collective behaviour of fish: Introducing Robofish</article-title>. <source>Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Herskin1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herskin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steffensen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Energy savings in sea bass swimming in a school: measurements of tail beat frequency and oxygen consumption at different swimming speeds</article-title>. <source>Journal of Fish Biology</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>376</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Svendsen1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Svendsen</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skov</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bildsoe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steffensen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Intra-school positional preference and reduced tail beat frequency in trailing positions in schooling roach under experimental conditions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Fish Biology</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>834</fpage>–<lpage>846</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Grunwald1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grunwald</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Headwaters of the zebrafish – emergence of a new model vertebrate</article-title>. <source>Nature reviews Genetics</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>724</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Miklsi1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miklósi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The zebrafish as a model for behavioral studies</article-title>. <source>Zebrafish</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Miller1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Quantification of shoaling behaviour in zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>184</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Spence1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlach</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The behaviour and ecology of the zebrafish, <italic>Danio rerio</italic></article-title>. <source>Biological Reviews</source> <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Buske1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buske</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Shoaling develops with age in Zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Progress in Neuro-Psychopharmacology and Biological Psychiatry</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1409</fpage>–<lpage>1415</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Miller2"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>From Schooling to Shoaling: Patterns of Collective Motion in Zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>)</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e48865</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Gerlai2"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lahav</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Drinks like a fish: zebra fish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) as a behavior genetic model to study alcohol effects</article-title>. <source>Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>773</fpage>–<lpage>782</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Mathur1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Use of zebrafish as a model to understand mechanisms of addiction and complex neurobehavioral phenotypes</article-title>. <source>Neurobiology of disease</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Miller3"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dydinski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Effects of nicotine and alcohol on zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) shoaling</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>240</volume>: <fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Grossman1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Utterback</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaikwad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Characterization of behavioral and endocrine effects of LSD on zebrafish</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>214</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Gerlai3"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>High-throughput behavioral screens: the first step towards finding genes involved in vertebrate brain function using zebrafish</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2609</fpage>–<lpage>2622</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Saverino1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saverino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The social zebrafish: behavioral responses to conspecific, heterospecific, and computer animated fish</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>191</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Abaid2"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abaid</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spinello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laut</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porfiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) responds to images animated by mathematical models of animal grouping</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>232</volume>: <fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>410</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Cahill1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Clock mechanisms in zebrafish</article-title>. <source>Cell and Tissue Research</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Kopman2"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porfiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Design, modeling, and characterization of a miniature robotic-fish for research and education in biomimetics and bioinspiration</article-title>. <source>IEEE/ASME Transactions on Mecha-tronics</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>483</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Rosenthal1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Assortative preferences for stripe patterns in danios</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>1063</fpage>–<lpage>1066</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Wong1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elegante</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elkhayat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tien</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Analyzing habituation responses to novelty in zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>208</volume>: <fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>457</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Bass1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>SLS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) responds differentially to stimulus fish: the effects of sympatric and allopatric predators and harmless fish</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>186</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Webster1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>AJW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>PJB</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Habitat-specific chemical cues influence association preferences and shoal cohesion in fish</article-title>. <source>Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Kolpas1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolpas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moehlis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frewen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kevrekidis</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Coarse analysis of collective motion with different communication mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Mathematical Biosciences</source> <volume>214</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Vicsek1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vicsek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Czirók</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Jacob</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shochet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Novel type of phase transition in a system of self-driven particles</article-title>. <source>Physical Review Letters</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>1226</fpage>–<lpage>1229</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Faul1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faul</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erdfelder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>G*Power 3: a flexible statistical power analysis program for the social, behavioral, and biomedical sciences</article-title>. <source>Behavior Research Methods</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Tien1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tien</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Dynamics of fish shoals: identifying key decision rules</article-title>. <source>Evolutionary Ecology Research</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>565</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Speedie1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Speedie</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Alarm substance induced behavioral responses in zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>188</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Breder1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Breder</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1946</year>) <article-title>Innate and acquired behavior affecting the aggregation of fishes</article-title>. <source>Physiological zoology</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Bode1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bode</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>How perceived threat increases synchronization in collectively moving animal groups</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source> <volume>277</volume>: <fpage>3065</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Maximino1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maximino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Brito</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva Batista</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herculano</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Measuring anxiety in zebrafish: a critical review</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source> <volume>214</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Plaut1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plaut</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Effects of fin size on swimming performance, swimming behaviour and routine activity of zebrafish <italic>Danio rerio</italic></article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Biology</source> <volume>203</volume>: <fpage>813</fpage>–<lpage>820</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Thomas1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janz</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Dietary selenomethionine exposure in adult zebrafish alters swimming performance, energetics and the physiological stress response</article-title>. <source>Aquatic toxicology (Amsterdam, Netherlands)</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0076123-Pritchard1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butlin</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Shoal choice in zebrafish, <italic>Danio rerio</italic>: the influence of shoal size and activity</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>1085</fpage>–<lpage>1088</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>